good morning
welcome to meditating with john rivaki
i'm a cognitive psychologist and
cognitive scientist at the university of
toronto
we're an academic and scientific manner
i study mindfulness a related phenomena
like
insight flow mystical experience
transformative experience higher states
of consciousness
the cultivation of wisdom and the
aspiration to enlightenment
i've also been practicing meditation
metacontemplation taichichuan and
chikang
for over 29 years in addition
i've been teaching all of those things
professionally for close to 20 years
so welcome this is a course if you're
joining us for the first time of course
you're welcome to stay
but there have been eight lessons so far
if you want to catch up on the previous
lessons go to links in the description
of this video
and you can catch up on those previous
lessons what normally happens is monday
is dharma day that's a day in which i
teach a lesson
i give a principle that builds on the
previous principles that i've taught
we usually do an experiential exercise
so you get a more direct
understanding of it and then we sit
together
tuesdays through fridays are sick days
we meet
we meet and sometimes review the dharma
that was taught on monday
and then we sit at the end of each day
monday through friday there is a q a
please keep your questions directed
towards the practice and the course that
i'm teaching right now
for those questions that are more
encompassing in nature
bubble buddhism or the relationship
between buddhism and stoicism or the
cultivation of wisdom
or responding current situation more
adaptively please join me
at 3 pm est every third friday of the
month where we live stream
q a so
today is our last sit day for the week
uh i would ask you if you could please
remember to like
this video stream it will raise the
visibility
in the youtube algorithm and that will
help me to
reach as many people as possible i'm
doing this
like gravis because i think it is a good
thing to do
is my way of trying to help people to
give them a deeper
access uh to uh to resiliency
and to add activity in these very
difficult and challenging times
okay i think that's all of our
announcements i'm glad that all of you
are showing up
i took a brief look at it and i'm just
so
i don't know maybe the try to think of
the right word that doesn't come across
as condescending but i'm very pleased
uh to see all of the community
involvement and the way of saying is
taking shape
it's really encouraging me uh to as i'm
thinking and considering
after we're done this 10-week meditation
and contemplation course
to extending it and showing you other
wisdom practices and spiritual exercises
from other traditions
and we can uh cultivate a wisdom singer
together so i'm very happy
to see that i hope uh it continues
all right so as i say today is a sip day
so please set your phones to do not
disturb
get ready in your posture and we will
begin
when i say begin
beginning
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate your
practice
with your everyday consciousness and
cognition perhaps by silently
reciting the promises to yourself
all right we have time for some
questions
uh lizzle van wyck hi lizzle uh
how important is it to have my knees
below hips during the sit and why
i have a knee injury and it's uh it's a
little strenuous
uh the point about getting the knees
below the hips really equal to the hips
is it takes the s curve out of your
spine so that when i relax
right i'm erect my stomach is open if i
don't have something underneath if my
hips
are not level it might if i just sit
down
um then what will happen is my spinal
curve
and my chest will collapse and um this
is a
this is a way of inhabiting your body
that is associated with anxiety
uh poor breathing habits uh so you'll
have less oxygen be more anxious
um so it's a challenge now on the other
hand
um if you have a knee injury remember
our principle here we never
endure we're always trying to reduce
we're always trying to educate to draw
forth
we're not ever just enduring so if your
knee is a problem
then i recommend you sit on a chair if
you sit on a chair
um then what you can do is you can sit
what's called egyptian posture
you're putting your feet in front of you
you put your hands on your knees then
you go through the centering and the
rooting
if you don't need to use the back of the
chair try not to if you're also having
back issues
uh because sometimes knee and back tend
to be related
because we uh they're we at least tend
to favor one leg or something like that
so if that is the case i don't know i'm
just saying
uh then after we've centered and rooted
you can lean back slightly and take the
pressure off
on the chair so uh we'll try sitting in
a chair and then going through the
centering and rooting
finding the core four and see if that
works better for you
we'll stein silverstone after following
a course for a while i get chills at
times while practicing mindfulness do
you why
yes this is very common um there's a
couple things probably going on
if we get to a place where we are
co-activating
the task focus network and the default
mode network and i've talked about this
earlier
or triggering both the sympathetic and
the parasympathetic system
we can get significant
uh stimulation of the vagus nerve system
um
and so there's ways in which parts of
the brain are all starting to talk to
each other
and then we get that kind of response
sometimes it's stronger in people
i remember when that first started
happening to me it was like an electric
shock was going through my body part of
why this particular course
in this particular set of practices the
psychology practices i'm teaching you
um is more prone to that is because this
since i'm what i'm teaching you is a
very embodied form
of mindfulness one of the criticisms i
have of just
sitting is it tends to get just into the
head
and it tends to not involve the body
um whereas the teaching i had in tai chi
chuan
and of course chi kung those are very
embodied forms of mindfulness and you
get
so you get a you get this sense of and i
use this
as a metaphor of energy uh moving
through your body
uh in this more embodied form of
mindfulness ultimately
i would argue it is much much better for
you because i think the disembodied
forms of mindfulness
are do not reach into the depths of our
existence and our embodiment
and they're not as adaptive and as
responsive and resilient
i know some people won't like to hear
that uh and i'm not saying
that a purely acidic practice is is not
good but there's clear cognitive science
that if you're doing a moving practice
you're you're kicking in the cerebellum
the cerebellum has more neurons in it
than all of your cortex
they're not organized to produce
cognition
or consciousness but what they do is
they first of all give you tremendous
physical balance and integrity
embodied but that also translates into
cognitive
balance and integrity and a balance and
integrity of consciousness
so engaging the cerebellum is a very
helpful thing to do
the kennedy high neck i can never get
through all
full motorcycle in 15 minutes change the
pace or take a long evening set take a
longer set
take a longer circuit if if that's okay
for you
and take a longer set there's something
about how you are working with
right the grain of your mind as some of
the traditions talk about
uh that needs to be respected right now
so i would say uh
try and do a longer set
mark the fever hello mark and i want to
thank mark marquez uh
in the sena and he's there and his
wonderful good humor
and i think his presence um is so
encouraging
and i believe it's encouraging to other
people so i wanted to thank mark for
that right now
uh this is the 200th question i'm
answering already
wow time goes hey tempest fugit
i have a practice i call zen sweeping
which is probably embodied flow
the flow you seem to talk about in
meditation seems like internally
embodied flow
yes mark that's right that's absolutely
correct in a way of
of conceptualizing it conceiving of
this works well for me in the rooting
step but i'm having issues with the flow
step
can you offer any sites to help me do
the flow stage better
so uh you
might want to try to see
the continuity between rooting and flow
so remember there's a stage in where
we're letting it flow
and if that's working for you in rooting
pay attention to what that
feels like remember the taste that tempo
the texture like the tenure
the timing right of your mind and body
what does that taste like in your mind
when you're letting it flow within
rooting try to create a felt sense of
that and then try to bring that felt
sense
into the areas you're trying to
cultivate your sense of flow
so i think that might help so
try to exact and make use of
the affordance of flow that's already
present within routing if the routing is
working well for you
okay so on fridays i have to go pretty
sharply um
but i really appreciate all the
questions uh
as always i want to thank you all for
joining and for participating and i want
to encourage that to keep it going
again please remember to like this video
it raises its availability
and helps me to help more people with it
um in connection with that if you could
please recommend
uh this video series to as many people
as you think could benefit from it
i would appreciate that always i want to
thank
my dear friend and techno major mar for
all his great works behind the scene
and i want to thank my beloved son jason
for all of his help he's always here
helping
please uh please subscribe to the
channel
if you subscribe to the channel you can
get notification of further videos
and on the channel you'll find my
awakening for the meaning crisis series
my voices with verbacy's
series other videos these will these
will those
lectures are uh in awakening and
discussions with people committed to the
integration of science and spirituality
and voices with reiki so there's these
lectures and discussions on many of the
topics
we're exploring here uh mindfulness
mystical experience and wisdom
overcoming self-deception
and getting more coupled and connected
to ourselves each other in the world
all of those all of those things
um a reminder finally we do this
every monday morning uh est
9 30 a.m mondays are dharma days
tuesday through fridays or sick day
every third
friday of the month is the live stream
for more general q a
thank you very much for your time and
attention remember continuity of
practice more important than quantity
there is no enemy worse than your own
mind
there is no ally greater than your own
take care everyone and i'll see you on
monday